<rss version="2.0"  	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"  	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"  	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"  	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"  	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"  	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"  	>      <channel>   	<title>Armed and Dangerous</title>   	<atom:link href="http://esr.ibiblio.org/?feed=rss2" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />   	<link>http://esr.ibiblio.org</link>   	<description>Sex, software, politics, and firearms. Life&#039;s simple pleasures...</description>   	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Sep 2010 10:19:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>   	<generator>http://wordpress.org/?v=2.8.4</generator>   	<language>en</language>   	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>   	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>   			<item>   		<title>Needling Haystack</title>   		<link>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2568</link>   		<comments>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2568#comments</comments>   		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2010 09:38:08 +0000</pubDate>   		<dc:creator>esr</dc:creator>   				<category><![CDATA[General]]></category>      		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2568</guid>   		<description><![CDATA[In mid-2009, just after Neda Soltan was shot down on a Tehran street, I was working with a group of hackers attempting to provide covert communications support to the Iranian dissident movement.  I blogged about it at the time, received my second death threat as a result, and had a couple of interesting conversations [...]]]></description>   			<content:encoded><![CDATA[><p>In mid-2009, just after Neda Soltan was shot down on a Tehran street, I was working with a group of hackers attempting to provide covert communications support to the Iranian dissident movement.  I blogged about it at the time, received my second death threat as a result, and had a couple of interesting conversations with the FBI.  Eventually I stopped working with the group; they made what I considered some serious mistakes of direction, and I was anyway beginning to doubt the principal&#8217;s claims of having an extensive contact network on the ground in Iran.</p>   <p>The group I was working with was deploying stealthed HTTP proxies and Tor nodes; my main technical contribution was a Squid configuration tuned to the purpose in ways I won&#8217;t discuss because the techniques might be useful against another tyranny someday. We knew of other groups using different technology;  one seemed to be organized around a program called Haystack and its designer, a guy named Austin Heap.</p>   <p>I had brief contact with Heap during that period.  Now I learn that he may have been a fraud.  <a href="http://www.slate.com/id/2267262/pagenum/all/">The Great Internet Freedom Fraud</a> all but accuses him of this.</p>   <p><span id="more-2568"></span></p>   <p>I&#8217;m blogging about this because, on the one hand, I had a few suspicions about Heap at the time.  On the other, neither my interactions with him nor (in my judgment) the public evidence quite supports the theory that he set out to scam people.  For whatever it&#8217;s worth, I think he started with good intentions, talked a bigger game than he was really capable of executing, and got in over his head.</p>   <p>There was a lot of that going around &#8211; including, very possibly, in the group I was working with.  To this day I don&#8217;t know what, if any, impact we actually had.  Could have been a lot.  Could have been nothing.  All I know is that someone apparently affiliated with the Iranian regime threatened to have me killed over it, and the FBI believed the threat was credible enough to talk to me about the whole deal. But that threat, too, could have been a phantom or fraud, and well I know it.</p>   <p>Why am I blogging about this now?  Partly because I think the Slate article overreached a bit in its implied accusations against Heap.  I was in the trenches with him and others who were trying to help the dissidents, and I think he&#8217;s owed just a bit more benefit of the doubt than he&#8217;s getting there.</p>   <p>But mainly I want to point out what this episode teaches about the epistemic problems of operating in a stealth mode, among a group that is trying to do operational security.  These problems are shared by spies, terrorists, and groups like the ones I was working with who are gaming against spies and terrorists.</p>   <p>The problem is this: to protect your network, and yourself, you have to accept that you are going to have relatively little information about what your network partners are doing and what their capabilities are.  In this instance, I didn&#8217;t <em>want</em> to know details about the scope or nature  of our on-the-ground network in Iran; I was, for some crucial weeks after the Neda Soltan shooting, our public contact person, and thus the most exposed to pressure by our adversaries.</p>   <p>The obvious problem was, my rationally-chosen ignorance left me unable to form judgments about whether people in my network were lying to me.  More subtly (and here we get back to what I think happened with Austin Heap) it left me unable to form judgments about whether they were <em>lying to themselves</em>. </p>   <p>Normally, I think I&#8217;m pretty good at detecting self-deception &#8211; face to face.  There are tells in affect, tone, and body language that you learn to spot after a few decades of peoplewatching that tell you a speaker is actively suppressing doubt about his own utterences (and these are slightly different than the tells for outright lying).  I&#8217;ve actually had to practice this; it&#8217;s one of the most important person-to-person leadership skills.  But it&#8217;s much more difficult to spot self-bullshitting over text links and chat, and I have little confidence that I can do that reliably.</p>   <p>Thus, my ties to this network depended on a high level of faith in my contacts.  It couldn&#8217;t be otherwise, because trying to gather information that might have allowed me to reason out the odds better might have jeopardized them, jeopardized the dissidents I was trying to help, jeopardized me, and blown the network.  As a direct consequence, my participation was fragile; when my contacts said and did things that eroded my faith in their judgment, I dropped out.</p>   <p>Here&#8217;s the next turn of the screw: I think living in that kind of informationally poor shadow-world makes it more likely that a well-intentioned but only marginally competent person will overcommit to others <em>and himself</em> in order to increase his influence, and eventually con himself into a role he can&#8217;t sustain.  Because who has the information to call bullshit soon enough to stop the escalation before it gets past little white lies?  </p>   <p>I suspect very strongly that this is the trap Austin Heap fell into. And I&#8217;m not sure my contacts weren&#8217;t down the same hole and my effort wasted.  I don&#8217;t think I can assign less than a 30% probability to that outcome.  </p>   <p>Still &#8211; even with that uncertainty I&#8217;d do it again, death threat and all.  Because I&#8217;m a man and an American and a libertarian, and all three of these entail duties. In the course of those duties, there are some sorts of risks that must be run; honor and ethics require it.  The risks I took, and am still taking as a result, were among them.</p>   <p>I don&#8217;t think my experience was unique; people who fight for good causes in shadow have, no doubt, been experiencing these problems since history began.  But I&#8217;m not sure I can extract any larger lesson here.   I don&#8217;t mean to excuse whatever lies Austin Heap may have told, but I do mean to suggest he may well have been his own first victim.</p>   ]]></content:encoded>   			<wfw:commentRss>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?feed=rss2&amp;p=2568</wfw:commentRss>   		<slash:comments>30</slash:comments>   		</item>   		<item>   		<title>Pessimistic anarchism</title>   		<link>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2556</link>   		<comments>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2556#comments</comments>   		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2010 10:55:31 +0000</pubDate>   		<dc:creator>esr</dc:creator>   				<category><![CDATA[General]]></category>      		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2556</guid>   		<description><![CDATA[I received email recently asking me to respond to an article in the Huffington Post, No Safe Harbor on Gulf Coast; Human Blood Tests Show Dangerous Levels of Toxic Exposure.  Questioner&#8217;s English wasn&#8217;t very good, but the question he was trying to pose was how market anarchists like myself can oppose government action to [...]]]></description>   			<content:encoded><![CDATA[><p>I received email recently asking me to respond to an article in the Huffington Post, <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/jerry-cope/no-safe-harbor-on-gulf-co_b_698338.html">No Safe Harbor on Gulf Coast; Human Blood Tests Show Dangerous Levels of Toxic Exposure</a>.  Questioner&#8217;s English wasn&#8217;t very good, but the question he was trying to pose was how market anarchists like myself can oppose government action to mitigate disasters like the Deepwater Horizon blowout, and what we have to say about the charge that corporate money is suppressing news of the full toll of the disaster.</p>   <p>What I had to say to him about that follows, slightly edited and expanded.  It&#8217;s as good an individual case as any to explain why my free-market anarchism is a result not of optimism about the perfectibility of markets but of profound pessimism about the limits of any sort of collective action by human beings.</p>   <p><span id="more-2556"></span></p>   <p>It does not matter for purposes of answering your question whether or not I think this article is factually accurate, since the situation it describes (environmental disaster followed by insidious long-term health effects that those responsible may be using corrupt means to cover up) represents a <em>possible</em> sort of collective-action problem with which anti-statists have to deal.</p>   <p>Our key insight is a pessimistic one: this is the sort of situation which, though individuals and markets don&#8217;t handle it well, isn&#8217;t actually handled well by governments either.  The fundamental mistake of statist thinking is to juxtapose the tragically, inevitably flawed response of individuals and markets to large collective-action problems like this one against the hypothetical perfection of idealized government action, without coping with the reality that government action is <em>also</em> tragically and inevitably flawed.</p>   <p>The implicit burden of the article, after all, is indignation that the government has been done too little and the wrong things.  What the author fails to grasp (because his thinking is warped by the religion of state-worship) is that this sort of dysfunction is not a sporadic accidental failure that could be corrected by sufficiently virtuous thoughts and deeds; it is an <em>essential</em> failure, entirely predictable from the incentives operating on all the actors (including the actors within government).</p>   <p>His sort of fantasy thinking implicitly throws a burden of proof on anarchists to construct a perfect response to something like the Deepwater Horizon disaster in a stateless system, or else have their critique of statism dismissed as heartless and inadequate. But the <em>correct</em> analysis is to notice that we can only do what we can only do, and compare the rationally expectable effectiveness of flawed government action against the rationally expectable effectiveness of flawed individual and market action.</p>   <p>The second level of error, once you get this far, is to require that the market action achieve a better outcome without including all the <em>continuing</em>, institutional costs of state action in the accounting. So, for example, other parts of the continuing costs of accepting state action to solve this individual toxic-exposure problem in the Deep Horizon aftermath is that Americans will be robbed every April 15th of five in twelve parts of their income (on average), and be randomly killed in no-knock drug raids.  And it&#8217;s no use protesting that these abuses are separable from the &#8220;good&#8221; parts  of government as long as you&#8217;re also insisting that the prospect of market failures is not separable from the good behavior of  markets!</p>   <p>Irrational anarchists believe that utopia is somehow achievable in a stateless system; they make the exact reciprocal error from statists,  believing that all evil proceeds from government.  Rational anarchists  like myself know that stateless systems will have tragic failures too, but believe after analysis that they would have fewer and smaller ones.</p>   <p>If this seems doubtful to you, do not forget to include all the great genocides of the 20th century in the cost of statism.  It was contemplating those that turned me into an anarchist &#8211; because that sort  of eruption of fire and blood, too, is not accidental but essential given the logic of state collectivism.</p>   ]]></content:encoded>   			<wfw:commentRss>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?feed=rss2&amp;p=2556</wfw:commentRss>   		<slash:comments>321</slash:comments>   		</item>   		<item>   		<title>The smartphone wars: What Gassée has to say</title>   		<link>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2561</link>   		<comments>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2561#comments</comments>   		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Sep 2010 00:34:14 +0000</pubDate>   		<dc:creator>esr</dc:creator>   				<category><![CDATA[General]]></category>      		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2561</guid>   		<description><![CDATA[This is interesting.  Jean-Louis Gassée, former head of Be Inc. and now a venture capitalist, has spotted what may be another prong of Google&#8217;s strategy; break the carriers&#8217; term-contract system by driving the price of smartphones so far down that customers don&#8217;t need  or want a carrier subsidy.      Here&#8217;s what he says:      The great news [...]]]></description>   			<content:encoded><![CDATA[><p>This is interesting.  Jean-Louis Gassée, former head of Be Inc. and now a venture capitalist, has spotted what may be another prong of Google&#8217;s strategy; break the carriers&#8217; term-contract system by driving the price of smartphones so far down that customers don&#8217;t need  or want a carrier subsidy.</p>   <p><span id="more-2561"></span></p>   <p>Here&#8217;s what he says:</p>   <blockquote><p>   The great news is Google wants to disintermediate the carriers. How do they do that? By working with the Android army of manufacturers and targeting the $89 price point. Once there, carrier subsidies are no longer needed, consumers are free to move from one carrier to another as they get a better deal, or as they buy a new gadget without having to beg for an ETF (Early Termination Fee) exemption.  </p></blockquote>   <p>I&#8217;m not sure why Gassée thinks $89 is a magic price point, and this paragraph appears in a post labeled <a href="http://www.mondaynote.com/2010/06/20/science-fiction-nokia-goes-android/">Science Fiction: Nokia goes Android</a>, but no matter.  Qualitatively, Gassée is certainly on to something.</p>   <p>There has to be <em>some</em> price point below which subsidies become unnecessary and the term-contract system collapses.   It may not be $89, but it&#8217;s probably bracketed by $50 and $100.  Maybe Google thinks the handset manufacturers really can push handset prices that low if the hardware people don&#8217;t have to pay for smartphone OS development.  It may be right; the underlying question is probably whether smartphones have any components that aren&#8217;t following a Moore&#8217;s Law cost curve.</p>   <p>(Until recently, I would have said &#8220;Aha! The display!&#8221;.  But it turns out the price of LCDs was being held artificially high by collusion among major manufacturers; the ring got busted in early 2009, and lawsuits are continuing.)</p>   <p>Well before we reach the point at which the term-contract system collapses, the declining bill-of-materials cost on a smartphone will put a hard squeeze on the amount carriers can afford to spend on software development &#8211; yet another strike against carrier skins.  This reinforces my conclusion that the time when crippling Android with customizations remains a viable strategy is limited.  It may be over already.</p>   <p>Gassée emphasizes an important fact that I first wrote about nearly two years ago, around the time the G-1 first shipped.  The drama with Apple is in many ways a distraction; Google&#8217;s medium-term strategic goal is to break the cell-carrier oligopoly &#8211; smash their profit margins and commoditize their function. Gassée doesn&#8217;t note that longer-term than that they&#8217;ll have to take on the fiber/cable oligopoly as well, but he is certainly not stupid enough to have missed this.</p>   <p>Gassée has spent a lot of time thinking about which way Nokia&#8217;s going to jump once it becomes apparent that its software strategy is a fragmented mess.  Like Piper Jaffray (and now me) he sees a move to Android as a strong possibility, but he raises another possibility.  What if Stephen Elop, the Microsoft alumnus they&#8217;ve tapped as CEO opts for Windows Phone 7?</p>   <p>I don&#8217;t think it will happen. It would combine all the present business disadvantages of Android with the disadvantages of a closed-source codebase controlled by someone else.  Nokia&#8217;s engineers would scream bloody murder, and Nokia&#8217;s stockholders would probably tar and feather Elop and ride him out of Finland on a rail. </p>   <p>Still, the possibility can&#8217;t be completely ruled out.  Large companies have certainly done more blatantly self-destructive things before.  The smartphone wars have been aspiring to the condition of low comedy ever since Steve Jobs said &#8220;You&#8217;re holding it wrong!&#8221;; a mad fling between Nokia and Microsoft would take them straight to opéra bouffe.</p>   ]]></content:encoded>   			<wfw:commentRss>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?feed=rss2&amp;p=2561</wfw:commentRss>   		<slash:comments>73</slash:comments>   		</item>   		<item>   		<title>The smartphone wars: Google goes Taoist, Microsoft uses the farce</title>   		<link>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2548</link>   		<comments>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2548#comments</comments>   		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Sep 2010 04:51:25 +0000</pubDate>   		<dc:creator>esr</dc:creator>   				<category><![CDATA[General]]></category>      		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2548</guid>   		<description><![CDATA[A few days ago, I observed that Google is not pushing back against cell carriers&#8217; lockdown of  Android phones as vigorously as I had expected in the wake of the Android 2.2 announcement.  If this Twitter rumor is true, Google locked horns with the carriers and lost that confrontation, leading to the semi-discontinuance [...]]]></description>   			<content:encoded><![CDATA[><p>A few days ago, I observed that Google is not pushing back against cell carriers&#8217; lockdown of  Android phones as vigorously as I had expected in the wake of the Android 2.2 announcement.  If <a href="http://twitter.com/Scobleizer/status/24025002113">this Twitter rumor</a> is true, Google locked horns with the carriers and lost that confrontation, leading to the semi-discontinuance of the Nexus One.  Does this mean the carriers have won the war?</p>   <p><span id="more-2548"></span></p>   <p>I think not. The good news is that the announcement of the T-Mobile G-2, which will run un-skinned Android, suggests that Google&#8217;s longer-term strategy is still working.  I have noted that the opportunity cost to the carriers of these unhelpful customizations is rising, propelled upward by increasing time-to-market pressures that force them to either drastically compress development schedules or run down-version releases of Android that sacrifice performance and customer appeal.</p>   <p>I still think the carriers will hang themselves, given enough rope &#8211; and that the third phase of the smartphone wars, in which carrier efforts to tame Android collapse of their own weight, is about to begin.  I&#8217;ve argued this much in a <a href="http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2534">previous post</a>; my point now is that Google&#8217;s smart move now is Taoist.  They don&#8217;t need to fight the carriers in any other way than by keeping the Android release tempo up and the time-to-market pressure on the carriers correspondingly high.</p>   <p>One of my commenters asked how Android customization by handset vendors (as opposed to the carriers) changes this picture.  Not much at all, actually; if anything, the time-to-market pressure is worse on them than it is on the carriers, because they have more competition.  Most places, the carriers&#8217; markets look like oligopolies, but the handset market has more scrappy small players &#8211; and this makes complete sense, since the financial mass required to build and maintain a cell network is so much larger than you need to hire some engineers and rent fab capacity.</p>   <p>The difference in time-to-market pressure has consequences; expect the handset vendors to try to shed the cost  of customizing Android faster than the carriers do.  Notably, I don&#8217;t think HTC Sense will survive very long, especially not if the G-2 (which is expected to be an unskinned HTC Magic) does well.  Crap like Sprint&#8217;s NASCAR branding will outlast it, because NASCAR will actually pay the carrier for that placement and offset Sprint&#8217;s development costs.</p>   <p>Of course, as the handset vendors stop customizing Android, the <em>carriers&#8217;</em> cost of differentiating Android will go up faster.  There&#8217;s only one way that game can end, really; carriers lose, and Google wins.  The carriers can&#8217;t get off the tiger any more, not with Android&#8217;s new-unit sales growth utterly demolishing every other smartphone OS worldwide.</p>   <p>Which brings us to Windows Phone 7. Microsoft actually had the audacity to throw a shipping party that included a <a href=" http://technolog.msnbc.msn.com/_news/2010/09/10/5087329-zombies-hearses-and-monster-trucks-mark-windows-phone-7-celebration?ocid=twitter">mock funeral for the iPhone</a>.  All that really needs to be said abut this is that the event was recorded by an Android phone.</p>   <p>I never thought I&#8217;d hear myself say this, but&#8230;I find I&#8217;m actually pitying Microsoft a little.  They&#8217;ve got <em>nothing</em>, no hand at all in this game.  Their desktop-computing monopoly not only won&#8217;t help them gain share, it&#8217;s an actual hindrance; carrier and handset-vendor execs understand precisely what Microsoft did to the PC market and are determined not to be Ballmer&#8217;s bitches.  Microsoft&#8217;s previous mobile products have been a string of money-losing duds followed by an outright disaster &#8211; the wicked knock on Windows Phone 7 you&#8217;re going to keep hearing is &#8220;next of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microsoft_Kin">Kin</a>&#8220;.</p>   <p>Brand power?  It is to laugh; if you ask a random consumer in 2010 whether &#8220;Android&#8221; or &#8220;Microsoft&#8221; has more positive associations, Android will win hands-down (high marks to Google for effectively flooding that zone). Really Microsoft&#8217;s only asset is financial mass; if it&#8217;s possible for anyone to outright buy their way into the smartphone-OS market,  they&#8217;re the outfit that can do it.  Of course, this would involve forgoing actual <em>profits</em>, which is a problem now that their legendary cash hoard has largely been spent on fruitless acquisitions and stock buybacks.</p>   <p>No, Google has nothing to fear from Microsoft&#8230;and isn&#8217;t that an indication of how much the world has changed?</p>   ]]></content:encoded>   			<wfw:commentRss>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?feed=rss2&amp;p=2548</wfw:commentRss>   		<slash:comments>43</slash:comments>   		</item>   		<item>   		<title>Engineering history</title>   		<link>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2545</link>   		<comments>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2545#comments</comments>   		<pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2010 10:31:37 +0000</pubDate>   		<dc:creator>esr</dc:creator>   				<category><![CDATA[General]]></category>      		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2545</guid>   		<description><![CDATA[On a mailing list I frequent, a regular expressed doubt about the possibility that very small subgroups of a society (less than 5% of its population) can cause large changes in the overall direction of its evolution without long historical timespans to work in.  But I know from experience that this can happen, because [...]]]></description>   			<content:encoded><![CDATA[><p>On a mailing list I frequent, a regular expressed doubt about the possibility that very small subgroups of a society (less than 5% of its population) can cause large changes in the overall direction of its evolution without long historical timespans to work in.  But I know from experience that this can happen, because I&#8217;ve lived it.  My explanation (lightly edited and expanded) follows.</p>   <p>Of particular note is my explanation of how engineering design can shape history.</p>   <p><span id="more-2545"></span></p>   <p>Sometimes, when society reaches a cusp point, the decisions of individuals and small groups can have very large downstream consequences that are even visibly large in the near term.</p>   <p>I have personally been present, and an actor, for at least two such hinge points of history: the finalization of the Internet design in 1983, and the mainstream emergence of open-source methods in the late 1990s.  Even in the relatively short time since it has become clear that these are game-changers on the civilizational level, with ripple effects that will shape the rest of human history.</p>   <p>There may be other ways for it to to happen, but the way I&#8217;ve seen it happen is that a few engineers make choices that have very large implications for centralization vs. decentralization and the prevalence of information asymmetry, then bake these into infrastructure before the political class notices that the outcome could have been different.</p>   <p>Thought experiment: imagine an Internet in which email and web addresses were centrally issued by government agencies, with heavy procedural requirements and no mobility &#8211; even, at a plausible extreme, political patronage footballs. What kind of society do you suppose eventually issues from that?</p>   <p>I was there in 1983 when a tiny group called the IETF prevented this from happening.  I had a <a href="http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2539">personal hand in preventing</a> it and yes, I knew what the stakes were.  Even then. So did everyone else in the room.</p>   <p>Thought experiment: imagine a future in which everybody takes for granted that all software outside a few toy projects in academia will be closed source controlled by managerial elites, computers are unhackable sealed boxes, communications protocols are opaque and locked down, and any use of computer-assisted technology requires layers of permissions that (in effect) mean digital information flow is utterly controlled by those with political and legal master keys. What kind of society do you suppose eventually issues from that?</p>   <p>Remember Trusted Computing and Palladium and crypto-export restrictions?  RMS and Linus Torvalds and John Gilmore and I and a few score other hackers aborted that future before it was born, by using our leverage as engineers and mentors of engineers to change the ground of debate.  The entire hacker culture at the time was <em>certainly</em> less than 5% of the population, by orders of magnitude.</p>   <p>And we may have mainstreamed open source just in time.  In an attempt to defend their failing business model, the MPAA/RIAA axis of evil spent years pushing for digital &#8220;rights&#8221; management so pervasively baked into personal-computer hardware by regulatory fiat that those would have become unhackable.  Large closed-source software producers had no problem with this, as it would have scratched their backs too.  In retrospect, I think it was only the creation of a pro-open-source constituency with lots of money and political clout that prevented this.</p>   <p>Did we bend the trajectory of society?  Yes. Yes, I think we did. It wasn&#8217;t a given that we&#8217;d get a future in which any random person could have a website and a blog, you know. It wasn&#8217;t even given that we&#8217;d have an Internet that anyone could hook up to without permission.  And I&#8217;m pretty sure that if the political class had understood the implications of what we were actually doing, they&#8217;d have insisted on more centralized control.  ~For the public good and the children, don&#8217;t you know.~</p>   <p>So, yes, sometimes very tiny groups can change society in visibly large ways on a short timescale.  I&#8217;ve been there when it was done; once or twice I&#8217;ve been the instrument of change myself.</p>   ]]></content:encoded>   			<wfw:commentRss>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?feed=rss2&amp;p=2545</wfw:commentRss>   		<slash:comments>55</slash:comments>   		</item>   		<item>   		<title>Eminent Domains: The First Time I Changed History</title>   		<link>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2539</link>   		<comments>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2539#comments</comments>   		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Sep 2010 13:18:40 +0000</pubDate>   		<dc:creator>esr</dc:creator>   				<category><![CDATA[General]]></category>      		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2539</guid>   		<description><![CDATA[In a day or two I plan to do a blog post on the way engineering decisions can be critically important at cusp points in the history of society.  In order for part of the argument in that post to make sense, my readers need to hear a story I&#8217;ve been hinting at in [...]]]></description>   			<content:encoded><![CDATA[><p>In a day or two I plan to do a blog post on the way engineering decisions can be critically important at cusp points in the history of society.  In order for part of the argument in that post to make sense, my readers need to hear a story I&#8217;ve been hinting at in comments for some time: the first time that I personally made a difference in the world at what I believe was history-changing scale, and how that happened.</p>   <p><span id="more-2539"></span></p>   <p>I think it was at the 1983 Usenix/UniForum conference (there is an outside possibility that I&#8217;m off by a year and it was &#8216;84, which I will ignore in the remainder of this report).  I was just a random young programmer then, sent to the conference as a reward by the company for which I was the house Unix guru at the time (my last regular job).  More or less by chance, I walked into the meeting where the leaders of IETF were meeting to finalize the design of Internet DNS.  </p>   <p>When I walked in, the crowd in that room was all set to approve a policy architecture that would have abolished the functional domains (.com, .net, .org, .mil, .gov) in favor of a purely geographic system.  There&#8217;d be a .us domain, state-level ones under that, city and county and municipal ones under that, and hostnames some levels down. All very tidy and predictable, but I saw a problem.</p>   <p>I raised a hand tentatively.  &#8220;Um,&#8221; I said, &#8220;what happens when people <em>move</em>?&#8221;</p>   <p>There was a long, stunned pause.  Then a very polite but intense argument broke out.  Most of the room on one side, me and one other guy on the other.</p>   <p>OK, I can see you boggling out there, you in your world of laptops and smartphones and WiFi.  You take for granted that computers are mobile.  You may have one in your pocket right now.  Dude, it was 1983.  <em>1983.</em>  The personal computers of the day barely existed; they were primitive toys that serious programmers mostly looked down on, and not without reason.  Connecting them to the nascent Internet would have been ludicrous, impossible; they lacked the processing power to handle it even if the hardware had existed, which it didn&#8217;t yet. Mainframes and minicomputers ruled the earth, stolidly immobile in glass-fronted rooms with raised floors.  </p>   <p>So no, it wasn&#8217;t crazy that the entire top echelon of IETF could be blindsided with that question by a twentysomething smartaleck kid who happened to have bought one of the first three IBM PCs to reach the East Coast.  The gist of my argument was that (a) people were gonna move, and (b) because we didn&#8217;t really know what the future would be like, we should be prescribing as much mechanism and as little policy as we could.  That is, we shouldn&#8217;t try to kill off the functional domains, we should allow both functional and geographical ones to coexist and let the market sort out what it wanted. To their eternal credit, they didn&#8217;t kick me out of the room for being an asshole when I actually declaimed the phrase &#8220;Let a thousand flowers bloom!&#8221;. </p>   <p>(I wish I could remember who the one guy who immediately jumped in on my side was.  I think it was <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Spencer">Henry Spencer</a>, but I&#8217;m not sure.)</p>   <p>The majority counter, at first, was basically &#8220;But that would be chaos!&#8221;  They were right, of course.  But I was right too.  The logic of my position was unassailable, really, and people started coming around fairly quickly.  It was all done in less than 90 minutes.  And that&#8217;s why I like to joke that the domain-name gold rush and the ensuing bumptious anarchy in the Internet&#8217;s host-naming system is <em>all my fault</em>.</p>   <p>It&#8217;s not true, really.  It isn&#8217;t enough that my argument was correct on the merits; for the outcome we got, the IETF had to be willing to let a n00b who&#8217;d never been part of their process upset their conceptual applecart at a meeting that I think was supposed to be mainly a formality ratifying decisions that had already been made in working papers. I give them much more credit for that than I&#8217;ll ever claim for being the n00b in question, and I&#8217;ve emphasized that every time I&#8217;ve told this story.</p>   <p>Now look at what we avoided.  With the chaos came a drastically decreased vulnerability to single-point failures &#8211;  and I mainly mean the institutional kind, not the technical kind.  If DNS addresses had been immobile and tied to individual legal jurisdictions, there would have been a far stronger case for keeping address issuance under government auspices (it&#8217;s not like phone numbers, which started out being privately issued on privately-owned infrastructure). The bad consequences would only have started with expense and bureaucratization; more than likely control of the Internet address space would have become, in many jurisdictions, a political instrument used to reward approved parties and control information flow.  </p>   <p>Not only would this have been a bad thing in itself, it would have set a negative precedent for centralizing other aspects of Internet governance that might well have hardened into stone by the time the technology was ready for the general public a decade later.  Those of you who think ICANN and fly-by-night registrars are a pain in the ass aren&#8217;t wrong, but you should be on your knees in thanks that we got a system with that much play and polycentrism in it.  We very nearly didn&#8217;t.</p>   <p>If I were a dimwitted egotist I&#8217;d claim to have saved the world, maybe.  But what really mattered is that I threw my disruption into a roomful of hackers with an innate distrust of hierarchy and a strong allergy to system designs with single-point vulnerability.  It was that shared culture that made the difference, more than me &#8211; it produced my objection, and it produced people ready to hear it.</p>   <p>Still.  It was my hand that went up.  <em>Anybody</em> who grokked that computers could be mobile could have changed history just then, but it happened to be me, and it was my first time.</p>   <p>UPDATE: It&#8217;s been pointed out that while the RFC-issuing group that became the IETF existed in 1983-1984, it did not formally constitute itself as the &#8220;Internet Engineering Task Force&#8221; until 1986.  So my use of the term here is anachronistic.</p>   ]]></content:encoded>   			<wfw:commentRss>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?feed=rss2&amp;p=2539</wfw:commentRss>   		<slash:comments>62</slash:comments>   		</item>   		<item>   		<title>The smartphone wars: a cautious cheer for T-Mobile</title>   		<link>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2534</link>   		<comments>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2534#comments</comments>   		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Sep 2010 19:47:16 +0000</pubDate>   		<dc:creator>esr</dc:creator>   				<category><![CDATA[General]]></category>      		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2534</guid>   		<description><![CDATA[T-Mobile announced the G-2 yesterday.  They were, of course, the first carrier to ship an Android phone when they released the G-1 back in 2008.  I think this announcement signals yet another phase change in the smartphone wars, in which carriers begin to back off the proprietary skins that have disfigured recent Android [...]]]></description>   			<content:encoded><![CDATA[><p>T-Mobile announced the G-2 yesterday.  They were, of course, the first carrier to ship an Android phone when they released the G-1 back in 2008.  I think this announcement signals yet another phase change in the smartphone wars, in which carriers begin to back off the proprietary skins that have disfigured recent Android releases.</p>   <p><span id="more-2534"></span></p>   <p><a href="http://www.dailytech.com/TMobile+G2+is+Official+PreSale+Starts+This+Month/article19578.htm">Press coverage</a> has it that the G-2 is an HTC device and will run a vanilla, un-skinned 2.2.  The hardware news is unsurprising; the G-1 was an HTC Dream, and an excellent fit for purpose.  Rumor all along has been that the G-2 would be a branded variant of the HTC Magic.</p>   <p>Vanilla 2.2 bucks a recent and unhappy trend of carrier devices running down-version Android with heavy skinning and (often) lockout of much-desired features like tethering.  I predicted this trend wouldn&#8217;t last as customers caught wise and began to vote with their feet, and the G-2 is significant because it gives them a major-carrier device to run to.  Inevitably, the G-2 will increase market pressure against skinning.</p>   <p>On that account, here&#8217;s a cautious cheer for T-Mobile. My wife and I became T-mobile users to get the G-1, and  it must be said that they&#8217;ve they&#8217;ve been notably non-unpleasant by carrier standards.  Coincidentally, we reached the point of needing to decide whether to re-up with them in the week just before the announcement, and swiftly agreed it was a no-brainer.  Their coverage meets our needs and their rates aren&#8217;t silly. They get additional points for two things: (1) It wasn&#8217;t difficult to get them to unlock my G-1, policy is that any customer in good standing can have that after 90 days and (2) when I got my Nexus One the service rep I talked with not only didn&#8217;t give me crap about changing phones on a plan designated &#8220;G-1&#8243;, he sounded frankly envious that I&#8217;d gotten an N1 to play with.  </p>   <p>Yes, you&#8217;re catching my implication correctly; I actually <em>like</em> my cell carrier.  T-Mobile still pulls crap like charging mucho bucks for SMS when the incremental cost of the service to them is zero, but compared to the sleazy control-freak moves their competition routinely gets up to they&#8217;re actually pretty nice.</p>   <p>The personal report has a larger point lurking in it.  When you&#8217;re the number 4 carrier, perpetually derided as playing catch-up and scrambling for market share, one of the ways you can compete is by &#8211; gasp &#8211; <em>not treating your customers like shit</em>.  And not actively crippling the devices you ship.  This seems to be the route T-Mobile is going.</p>   <p>There are features of the evolving smartphone market that are pushing in this direction, anyway.  One is the increasing release tempo, driven by the number of handset manufacturers who want to get in on the action.  Symbolically, Nokia just sacked its CEO; as one of my commenters correctly noted, &#8220;No doubt this is a direct result from the failure to compete in the US smartphone market&#8221;.  They&#8217;re going to be trying harder.  This means that time to market is going to become an ever more pressing issue for new hardware rollouts, increasing the opportunity cost of vendor skinning.</p>   <p>Sure, the vendors can try to put the brakes on the hardware-release tempo.  But unless they actively collude it&#8217;s not going to happen &#8211; there&#8217;s too much marketing advantage to being first to hit the street with sexy new hardware, as we&#8217;ve seen for example with the EVO 4G, and the handset vendors will be upping the tempo in response to competition in <em>their</em> market. As product cycles shorten, increasing deadline pressure on the Android porting process means vendor customization costs are going to rocket, negating a significant part of Android&#8217;s cost advantage. </p>   <p>We can be very specific about the issues with vendor skins.  Their only advantage to customers is in the opportunity to improve stock Android&#8217;s user interface, which is a weak justification because it doesn&#8217;t actually suck to begin with.  The problem is that they function mainly as cover for various forms of carrier control.  In increasing order of annoyance, we can list (1) obtrusive branding, (2) uninstallable advertising/crapware paid for by business partners, (3) hijacking of the app store, and (4) data-usage caps, especially disabling of tethering and WiFi hotspot features.</p>   <p>Customers are bound to notice what a shitty deal this is, creating a marketing opportunity for a carrier that&#8217;s willing not to play these games.  The true significance of the G-2 announcement is that by trumpeting stock Android 2.2, T-Mobile is kicking its competitors right where it will hurt and shortening the lifetime of the skin-your-phones-skin-your-customers strategy.  As I&#8217;ve previously noted, I think Google is counting on this dynamic. </p>   <p>If carrier skins actually functioned as effective differentiators they&#8217;d be better able to justify their increasing opportunity costs.  But the carriers&#8217; own marketing suggests they&#8217;re not &#8211; notice how hardware-focused their new-product pitches are?  One suspects that various attempts to hype their custom interfaces didn&#8217;t survive focus-group testing, and no wonder when they mainly subtract value rather than adding it.  </p>   <p>In sum, I predict that the smartphone wars are about to enter phase three.  Phase one began with the Android launch and was dominated by a face-off with Apple iOS that Android won, rocketing past it in U.S. market share and reaching global market-share parity (soon to be dominance).  The theme of phase two, which began a few months before the Nexus One was canned off Google&#8217;s web store, was increasing attempts by carriers to stuff the Android genie back in the bottle by skinning.  </p>   <p>Phase three begins with the G-2 launch and will feature an accelerating collapse of carrier attempts to control and corral Android. They&#8217;ll be ended by customer pushback and time-to-market pressures on product development. This will throw the carriers into the exact kind of competition they most want to avoid &#8211; directly on price and quality of network provisioning.  Bad news for them, but great news for everyone else.</p>   ]]></content:encoded>   			<wfw:commentRss>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?feed=rss2&amp;p=2534</wfw:commentRss>   		<slash:comments>32</slash:comments>   		</item>   		<item>   		<title>The social utility of hacker humor</title>   		<link>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2520</link>   		<comments>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2520#comments</comments>   		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Sep 2010 12:36:20 +0000</pubDate>   		<dc:creator>esr</dc:creator>   				<category><![CDATA[General]]></category>      		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2520</guid>   		<description><![CDATA[I&#8217;ve been doing a lot of work recently on an ancient project of mine, C-INTERCAL, that&#8217;s an implementation of the longest-running joke in the history of computer languages.  It&#8217;s an implementation, begun in 1990, of a language conceived in 1972 as a parody of programming languages of the 1960s.  Now it&#8217;s nearly 40 [...]]]></description>   			<content:encoded><![CDATA[><p>I&#8217;ve been doing a lot of work recently on an ancient project of mine, <a href="http://catb.org/esr/intercal/">C-INTERCAL</a>, that&#8217;s an implementation of the longest-running joke in the history of computer languages.  It&#8217;s an implementation, begun in 1990, of a language conceived in 1972 as a parody of programming languages of the 1960s.  Now it&#8217;s nearly 40 years later, and yet some skilled hackers are still investing their time into fixing bugs, shipping releases, and even (gasp!) documenting the thing.</p>   <p>That&#8217;s a lot of effort to plow into a joke, and some people don&#8217;t get why.  But there are parallels elsewhere: consider, for example, the venerable custom of issuing spoof Internet standards, published through the same channels as the real RFCs, on every April 1st. Behaviors like INTERCAL or the spoof RFCs don&#8217;t usually persist as long as these have without some powerful reason behind them.</p>   <p><span id="more-2520"></span></p>   <p>I got a clue about this in the early 1990s when I was working on the Jargon File, another artifact with aspects of a joke that many hackers take very seriously indeed.  I had been invited to a sort of cultural-studies conference run by the Getty Foundation at which a bunch of anthropologists and folklorists were trying to get their heads around hacker culture <em>as a culture</em>,  using me more or less as a star informant.   </p>   <p>I was talking with one, and asked what her sorts of questions cultural anthropologists normally ask about cultures they&#8217;re doing fieldwork on.  She thought for a moment and said: &#8220;What&#8217;s the ritual calendar?  What are the high holy days of mandatory observance?&#8221;  It took me a bit of thought to understand why this is an important question, but it certainly is one.  The high holy days of a culture encode the myths and values it most celebrates.</p>   <p>I figuratively scratched my head and said &#8220;Uh, I dunno&#8230;I don&#8217;t think of any *HOLY SHIT*&#8230;.yes, actually, I can.  April Fool&#8217;s Day!&#8221;  And then I explained about the Joke RFCs and April Fool USENET parodies.  And we gazed upon each other with a feeling of discovery, for it was clear to both of us that we had grasped something important.</p>   <p>There are lots of things that can help define a culture.  Shared artifacts.  Shared myths &#8211; and by &#8220;myth&#8221; I don&#8217;t necessarily mean a falsehood, it can be real history interpreted in a value-laden or normative way. Shared taboos. Shared attitudes. And shared jokes.  One of the things that can help define a culture is &#8220;we are a people who laugh at the same things&#8221;.</p>   <p>INTERCAL, and the joke RFCs, and the in-jokes in the Jargon File, all have an important gatekeeping function for the hacker culture.  Hackers get why these things are funny, the same way they get why a feature request from Donald Knuth is like unto a commandment from $DEITY ($DEITY is yet another venerable hacker joke &#8211; it expands as &#8220;insert choice of god here&#8221;).  These artifacts are like the famous quip about jazz that if you need to have it explained to you you&#8217;ll never get it &#8211; a defining mystery that selects not merely for technical competence for but a certain posture of mind.  And induces it, too&#8230;</p>   <p>The people who write and maintain these jokes are expressing and reifying hacker values.  This is especially important for us, because our avenues of cultural transmission are in some ways quite restricted.  We don&#8217;t have a material culture; we use and borrow the  tangible artifacts of the culture(s) around us, but we don&#8217;t really have any of our own other than ephemera like T-shirts and mugs and a few toys from ThinkGeek. Nor do we have generational transmission in the normal sense; almost nobody gets to learn hacker folklore at a parent&#8217;s knee (although I know one <a href="http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=173">exceptional family</a> that comes close to this).</p>   <p>Here is, as it were, the punch line: April Fool&#8217;s Day is the hackers&#8217; only annual day of fixed observance in part because shared jokes are more central to our identity than they are in most cultures.  Which takes us back to INTERCAL; the programmer (or would-be programmer) who stumbles across it, reads, and begins to laugh, is becoming one of us.  Is, in fact, <em>making</em> himself one of us.  He is acquiring, by transmission through its jokes, the hacker posture of mind.  Much the same could be said, for example, of the infamous <a href="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc1149.html">RFC 1149</a> (A Standard for the Transmission of IP Datagrams on Avian Carriers).</p>   <p>The joke gets funnier, and the cultural transmission mechanism more effective, as the material around it more exactly reflects the serious values of the culture.  Thus, INTERCAL has to be an actual working compiler for a Turing-complete language, and its maintainers have evolved it from a scratchy one-off into a near-spotless example of good practice &#8211; clean, well-documented code using up-to-date tools and version control and with a regression-test suite.  In fact you can look back through the INTERCAL code, as I recently did, and see in it a potted history of how key practices in software tools, version control, documentation, testing and software distribution have evolved in the the last twenty years. From shar archives to tarballs; from no version control to centralized version control to distributed; from flat-text documentation to groff to texinfo to asciidoc; the assimilation of the Web; and, recently, an increasing focus on development by test.</p>   <p>There are messages on several levels here: one of the most important is that hackers are expected to be such dedicated craftsmen that they work to contemporary high standards even when the project is an intrinsically ridiculous museum piece.  In a similar spirit, the best joke RFCs are such immaculately deadpan parodies of standards language that if you&#8217;re not careful you can read several paragraphs in before you realize you are up to your eyeballs in satire.</p>   <p>This is odder than it may appear at first.  It is not just that hackers use technical humor to maintain an ironic distance from the machinery of software production they are so intimate with. It&#8217;s that this ironic distance, this affectionate parody, is one of the core observances of hacker culture &#8211; actually <em>definitional</em> of it.  We have a term for this borrowed from SF fandom; &#8220;ha ha only serious&#8221;, and I can&#8217;t think of any real parallel to it elsewhere; even circus clowns don&#8217;t celebrate their art by making satires of it.</p>   <p>A non-hacker might well ask &#8220;Why do I care?&#8221;  Which is a good question; it&#8217;s all very well that hackers have invented a cute little subculture around themselves, and may be academically interesting that acculturation by ha-ha-only-serious is important there.  But does the existence of this culture and these mechanisms mean anything to anyone else but anthropologists?  Is there any broader social utility here?</p>   <p>Yes, there is.  The jokes and the culture they figure forth matters because every once in a while something erupts out of them that is a game changer on a civilization-wide level.  Two of the big ones were the Internet and open-source software.  These two movements were intimately intertwined with hacker culture, both produced by it and productive of it.  The origins of our tribe go back a bit further than either technology, but we have since re-invented ourselves as the people who make that stuff work.</p>   <p>And I don&#8217;t mean &#8220;make it work&#8221; in a narrow technical sense, either.  As long as there are people who laugh at INTERCAL and RFC1149 and the Unix koans of Master Foo, and recognize themselves in the Jargon File, those same people will care passionately that computing technology is an instrument of liberation rather than control. They won&#8217;t be able to help themselves, because they will have absorbed inextricably with the jokes some values that are no joke at all. High standards of craftsmanship; a subversive sense of humor; a belief in the power of creative choice and voluntary cooperation; a spirit of individualism and playfulness; and not least, a skepticism about the pretensions of credentialism, bureaucracy and authority that is both healthy and bone-deep.</p>   <p>These are not trivial qualities in people who who have their hands on the controls of what may be the most critical layer of shared infrastructure in today&#8217;s computer-dependent civilization.  Someday, the spirit of hacker humor might head off any number of grim futures.  In fact, I think it not unlikely that it already has.</p>   ]]></content:encoded>   			<wfw:commentRss>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?feed=rss2&amp;p=2520</wfw:commentRss>   		<slash:comments>95</slash:comments>   		</item>   		<item>   		<title>The smartphone wars: a global perspective</title>   		<link>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2528</link>   		<comments>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2528#comments</comments>   		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2010 10:29:37 +0000</pubDate>   		<dc:creator>esr</dc:creator>   				<category><![CDATA[General]]></category>      		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2528</guid>   		<description><![CDATA[While doing some research to check an assertion made by a commenter on More dispatches from the smartphone front I ran across excerpts from a very interesting report from investment analysts at Piper Jaffray on global smartphone market share and how they expect it to change in the next few years.   I can&#8217;t get at [...]]]></description>   			<content:encoded><![CDATA[><p>While doing some research to check an assertion made by a commenter on <a href="http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2512">More dispatches from the smartphone front</a> I ran across <a href="http://www.zdnet.com/blog/btl/android-to-control-half-of-smartphone-market-say-analysts/38881">excerpts</a> from a very interesting report from investment analysts at Piper Jaffray on global smartphone market share and how they expect it to change in the next few years. </p>   <p>I can&#8217;t get at the full report, as Piper Jaffray has it paywalled and sells it to customers.  But I have to say that for bankers the excerpts I can see make them look pretty smart to me.  They&#8217;ve suggested a scenario for a radical change in market conditions that I actually think is quite plausible.</p>   <p><span id="more-2528"></span></p>   <p>Before I get into that, let&#8217;s consider what they have to say about current conditions. For months I&#8217;ve been hearing a story from commenters overseas that my prediction of near-term and irreversible Android dominance was founded on a U.S.-centric view that ignores structural differences in foreign markets.  According to this apologetic, Apple&#8217;s U.S. market-share crash since 4Q2009 is  really a result of it being bundled with  AT&#038;T&#8217;s crappy network.  Overseas, I was told, where unlocked phones are normal and carriers hawk SIM cards instead of tied hardware, Apple&#8217;s iOS is doing much better and still leads Android.</p>   <p>Of course, the prediction that goes with this that as soon as AT&#038;T&#8217;s U.S. exclusive ends in 2012 and iOS goes multicarrier, we will all learn that every Android customer in the known universe really wanted an iPhone and Android&#8217;s market share will collapse like a pricked balloon.  (Bear in mind this prediction has been enthusiastically seconded by the same fanboys that said Apple&#8217;s falloff in Q1 was due to customers holding off purchases until the iPhone4 came out and surely, <em>surely</em> Android&#8217;s market share would then collapse like a pricked balloon.  Well, we know how <em>that</em> rosy fantasy died.  iPhone4 didn&#8217;t even slow the rate of decline noticeably.) </p>   <p>Here&#8217;s another dose of cold hard reality: the belief that Apple is beating Android overseas is (according to Piper Jaffray) mythical.  They&#8217;re expecting final market share figures for 2010 to show iOS up by just 1% at 15.9% to 14.9%.  Backing this up is a <a href="http://www.canalys.com/pr/2010/r2010081.html">report from Canalys</a> that puts iOS&#8217;s 2Q2010 global share at 13% and, though it doesn&#8217;t give a figure, says the momentum is all with Android.  According to IDC, <a href="http://www.zdnet.com/blog/btl/apple-iphone-smartphone-market-share-surges-rim-slips/34181">Apple itself only claims 16%</a>.  And Gartner Research <a href="http://phandroid.com/2010/08/12/android-overtakes-apples-in-world-wide-market-share-according-to-gartner/">says</a> that as of August Android actually leads at 17% to Apple&#8217;s 14.2%!</p>   <p>The picture is clear: (1) iOS and Android are now at or near a statistical dead heat in global market share, and (2) every analyst expects Android to gain dramatically in the near future. What I notice in the data that they&#8217;re not saying is this: the world seems only to be lagging smartphone-OS trends in the U.S. by four to six months, suggesting that carrier bundling in the U.S. is having relatively little effect on those trends.</p>   <p>This puzzled me when I first tried to understand it, but I think I get it now.  The data only make sense if the rate at which U.S. consumers replace their phones (and move to Android) is substantially faster than their contract-expiration cycle.  The typical contract term in the U.S. is two years; if the rates match we&#8217;d expect to see a trend lag of a half cycle, about twelve months.  This is clearly not what&#8217;s happening.  The U.S. market looks more like the (unbundled) worldwide smartphone market than one might expect.</p>   <p>I can only guess why U.S. customers are replacing their phones that fast, but the simplest hypothesis seems also the most likely: a truly massive move is on from dumb &#8220;feature&#8221; phones to smartphones (and Piper Jaffray&#8217;s report agrees with my guess).  I think Android isn&#8217;t mainly stealing present customers from Apple; instead it&#8217;s doing hugely better among customers up-migrating from hardware like my old Samsung VT660.   And I don&#8217;t think we need to look much further than price for a reason; Android phones are cheaper and Apple just isn&#8217;t justifying its price premium for most. I also think the most plausible model is one in which once users land on a smartphone their choice is fairly stable, though with erosion towards Android continuing at a low rate. </p>   <p>That&#8217;s what&#8217;s happening now.  What comes next?</p>   <p>The consensus scenario among most of these analysts seems to be that Android clobbers the living snot out of  iOS in 2011, with its growth being especially strong in Asia.  Canalys is emphatic on this last point, and it makes sense; those customers are more price-sensitive than Americans.  But Piper Jaffray thinks something even more dramatic is going to happen.</p>   <p>Piper Jaffray thinks that Nokia and RIM are hardware companies in their DNA, and are soon going to be forced to face up to the fact that they&#8217;re just not very good at software &#8211; not good enough to compete with Google, anyway.  It&#8217;s expecting one or both of them to fold and jump to Android in 2011.  The ZDNet report on the Piper Jaffray study says there&#8217;s already been one bloody internal battle at RIM about this.</p>   <p>On due consideration, I think this is plausible and that I really should have spotted this possibility before Piper Jaffray did.  It&#8217;s following out the same pro-Android logic I did many months ago about software development being a cost sink for handset manufacturers that they&#8217;d best get rid of. Probably the only thing stopping Nokia is the amount of money and prestige they&#8217;ve sunk into Symbian, but it has to be dawning on them now that Android has Symbian seriously outgunned.  (I actually thought the Nokia acquisition of Symbian smelled faintly of doom back in 2008 before Android was a real factor.  I wasn&#8217;t sure why, there was  just that odor about it to me.)</p>   <p>So the international question reduces to this: is Android going to swamp iOS quickly on more less smooth continuation of present trends, or are Nokia and RIM going to fold and shuffle their userbases into the Android column even faster?  Not a lot of good news on the Rialto for Apple fans, and I suspect it&#8217;s  going to get worse before it gets worse.</p>   ]]></content:encoded>   			<wfw:commentRss>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?feed=rss2&amp;p=2528</wfw:commentRss>   		<slash:comments>120</slash:comments>   		</item>   		<item>   		<title>More dispatches from the smartphone front</title>   		<link>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2512</link>   		<comments>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2512#comments</comments>   		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2010 22:08:01 +0000</pubDate>   		<dc:creator>esr</dc:creator>   				<category><![CDATA[General]]></category>      		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2512</guid>   		<description><![CDATA[Four days ago I blogged about upgrading my old G-1 to CyanogenMOD and complained that the mod&#8217;s home site contained no high-level overview of the modding process to help pepople understand all the details in the modding instructions for individual devices.   It took some days of research, but I have now fixed that problem.  I [...]]]></description>   			<content:encoded><![CDATA[><p>Four days ago I blogged about upgrading my old G-1 to CyanogenMOD and complained that the mod&#8217;s home site contained no high-level overview of the modding process to help pepople understand all the details in the modding instructions for individual devices.</p>   <p>It took some days of research, but I have now <a href="http://wiki.cyanogenmod.com/index.php?title=Overview_of_Modding">fixed that problem</a>.  I had that narrative description reviewed by experts on the IRC #cyanogenmod IRC channel while I was writing it, so it&#8217;s an outsider view with insider correctness.</p>   <p><span id="more-2512"></span></p>   <p>In other news, see <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/android-share-of-mobile-web-use-soaring-iphone-falling-2010-9">Android&#8217;s Share Of Mobile Web Use Soaring, iPhone Falling</a>.  If that share is tracking installed base accurately, Android installed base will pass iOS&#8217;s sometime between the beginning of December 2010 and mid-February 2011.  This is just mildly more pessimistic than my forecast months ago of a crossover in 4Q2010, but it also needs bearing in mind that iOS webshare includes iPads as well as iPhones, and iPads don&#8217;t yet have effective competition.  Thus the usage figures probably underestimate the rate of share decline for iPhones alone.</p>   <p>All indications continue to be that the iPhone is collapsing towards the same status of high-margin niche product with single-digit market share that has been the historic norm for Apple.  The Apple fanboys who think that smooth UI and industrial design trump freedom from vendor lock-in and everything else (and champion the walled-garden content model!) have a lot more crow still to eat. I expect to enjoy every second of serving it to them.</p>   <p><a href="http://www.zdnet.com/blog/btl/the-dirty-little-secret-about-google-android/38260">The dirty little secret about Google Android</a> suggests that Android&#8217;s triumph may not be a good thing after all.  In its reading of events, the withdrawal of the Nexus One signals that Google is allowing cellphone carriers to seize back the power over feature lists that it seemed to be claiming with the announcement of the Android 2.2 feature list.  And it&#8217;s true that some Android devices now have unhelpful carrier customizations that lock out features like USB tethering and lock in crapware apps that users might qet to delete.</p>   <p>Months ago, I thought that Google walking away from a deal with Verizon meant that Google was going to get tough with the carriers about not crippling Android 2.2.  I may have been wrong about that, or right at the time but something has changed in their calculations since.  They&#8217;re not resisting feature deletion and crapware with the intensity I expected then.</p>   <p>While this is cause for concern, it&#8217;s not yet time for alarm. I pointed out in <a href="http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=2021">Flattening the Smartphone Market</a>, five months ago, that  what&#8217;s really dangerous to the carriers is <em>comparability of product</em>.  When customers start asking questions like &#8220;Sprint Android has tethering, why don&#8217;t I?&#8221; and &#8220;Why have you blocked me from deleting apps that you privileged?&#8221; vendor attempts to control features are living on borrowed time, whatever Google does or doesn&#8217;t do.  </p>   <p>The existence of aftermarket upgrades like CyanogenMod for phones produced in huge volumes sharpens the edge of that blade by making unlocked, user-controlled phones a reality.  Projects like OpenMoko&#8217;s FreeRunner are worthy and wonderful but can&#8217;t capture the economies of scale that come from expected production runs in the hundreds of millions; thus they&#8217;re doomed to remain expensive niche toys for hackers.  CyanogenMOD is more effective because it co-opts the commercial success of Android and the financial mass of the handset manufacturers.</p>   <p>Which brings me back to CyanogenMOD documentation.  Anything that lowers the barrier to installing that mod on mass-market phones increases the pressure on the carriers.  The amount of grief they can inflict on their customers via Android customization is now bounded above by the hassle cost of installing CyanogenMOD.  By making that installation easier, I have directly attacked their lock-in.</p>   <p>Are Google&#8217;s strategic planners counting on efforts like CyanogenMOD to help fight their corner?  You betcha.  They learned how to think about the open-source long term from me (I still have Larry and Sergei&#8217;s fanmail from 1998 to prove that), and they&#8217;re not stupid.  If I can see where product comparability is leading, I&#8217;m bound to assume that so can they &#8211; and it recommends a very Taoist strategy.  That is, rather than fight the carrier oligopoly for openness directly, give them enough rope to hang themselves with &#8211; and let their customers do the actual hanging.</p>   ]]></content:encoded>   			<wfw:commentRss>http://esr.ibiblio.org/?feed=rss2&amp;p=2512</wfw:commentRss>   		<slash:comments>41</slash:comments>   		</item>   	</channel>   </rss> 